<tool id="EMBOSS: compseq14" name="compseq" version="5.0.0">
  <description>Count composition of dimer/trimer/etc words in a sequence</description>
  <requirements><requirement type="package" version="5.0.0">emboss</requirement></requirements>
  <command>compseq -sequence $input1 -outfile $out_file1 -word $word -frame $frame -auto</command>
  <inputs>
    <param format="fasta" name="input1" type="data">
      <label>On query</label>
    </param>
    <param name="word" size="4" type="text" value="2">
      <label>Size of word (window) to count</label>
    </param>
    <param name="frame" type="select">
      <label>Frame to inspect</label>
      <option value="0">All Frames</option>
      <option value="1">Frame 1</option>
      <option value="2">Frame 2</option>
      <option value="3">Frame 3</option>
    </param>
  </inputs>
  <outputs>
    <data format="compseq" name="out_file1" />
  </outputs>
  <tests>
    <test>
      <param name="input1" value="2.fasta"/>
      <param name="word" value="2"/>
      <param name="frame" value="0"/>
      <output name="out_file1" file="emboss_compseq_out.compseq"/>
    </test>
  </tests>
  <help>

-----

    You can view the original documentation here_.
    
    .. _here: http://emboss.sourceforge.net/apps/release/5.0/emboss/apps/compseq.html

------

**What it does**

compseq calculates the composition of words of a specified length (dimer, trimer etc) in the input sequence(s). The word length is user-specified. The unique sequences (words), their observed count, observed frequency, expected frequency and (observed / expected) frequency are written to the output file. The (observed / expected) frequency highlights any words with unusually high (or low) occurence in the input sequences.

**Input**

compseq reads a normal sequence(s). 

**Output**

The output format consists of:

Header information and comments are preceeded by a '#' character at the start of the line.

The Word size and the Total count are then given on separate lines,

The headers of the columns of results are preceeded by a '#'

The results columns are: the sub-sequence word, the observed frequency, the expected frequency (which will be read from the input file if one is given, else it is a simple inverse of the number of words of the size specified that can be constructed), the ratio of the observed to expected frequency.

After a blank line at the end, the results of 'Other' words is given - this is the number of words with a sequence which has IUPAC ambiguity codes or other unusual characters in. 

  </help>

  <citations>
    <citation type="doi">10.1016/S0168-9525(00)02024-2</citation>
    <citation type="doi">10.1101/gr.5578007</citation>
  </citations>


</tool>
